A Guide to the Aram Saroyan Papers 1978.0004
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Aram Saroyan Papers
undated, 1950-1977
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1978.0004
5.6 Linear Feet
Aram Saroyan was born in 1943, the son of famous American writer and playwright William Saroyan. In addition to several volumes of poetry, Saroyan has published several autobiographical novels, including The Street, in addition to a critical study of beat poet Lew Welch and a biography of his father.
Biography
Aram Saroyan was born 25 September 1943, the son of playwright William Saroyan and Carol (Marcus) Saroyan, later Carol Matthau. He attended high school at the Trinity School in New York City. He attended college at the University of Chicago, New York University, and Columbia University, but never completed a college degree. In the late 1960s Saroyan experimented with marijuana and began to develop a career as a poet. Director Mike Nichols wanted to cast Saroyan in the lead of his movie The Graduate, but Saroyan walked away from the part in order to focus on his writing. His life experiences at this time are described in his novel, The Street.
Scope and Content
This collection begins Saroyan's incoming correspondence for the years 1975-1977. Note that much of this correspondence consists of returned manuscript submissions, and thus numerous fair copies of Saroyan's own poems and reviews can be found within the correspondence. Notable correspondents include: Donald Allen, Richard Avedon, Ed Dorn, Gerald Hausman, Dick Higgins, David Kherdian, Kenneth Koch, Timothy Leary, Gerard Malanga, Carol and Walter Matthau, Rod McKuen, Joel Oppenheimer, George Plimpton, Charles Plymell, William Saroyan, Gary Snyder, Anne Waldman, and Philip Whalen. Note that a small portion of the personal correspondence is addressed to Saroyan's wife and children rather than to Saroyan himself.
At the end of the correspondence is a set of audio recordings made by Saroyan. One tape consists of a Lew Welch interview (probably copied from someone else) and Saroyan's own tapings of talks with Joanne Kyger, Magda Cregg, Gary Snyder and Philip Whalen.
The second box of the collection includes photocopies of Saroyan's periodical publications from 1975-1977, both prose and poetry. Most of this box is taken up by Saroyan's manuscripts and drafts from this period. Manuscript holdings include a good deal of poetry, and complete drafts of the volume O My Generation and Other Poems. The collection also contains all of Saroyan's materials for his book on Lew Welch, including large excerpts from a typescript of Welch's correspondence. Some of Saroyan's miscellaneous personal papers can be found at the end of the collection.
Original copies of newspapers and periodicals in which Saroyan's work appears were included with the donation, but only copies of Saroyan's articles were preserved. In addition, original copies of a Rolling Stone issue featuring Richard Avedon (RS224, October 21, 1976) and a California Living newspaper supplement (San Francisco Examiner, June 12, 1977) that only briefly mentions Saroyan were removed from the collection.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence, ( 1975-1977 )
Series II: Audio cassettes, ( 1969-1977 )
Series III: Publications, ( undated, 1950-1977 )
Acquisition Information
Collection purchased from Aram Saroyan in 1978.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Poems; Twentieth century.; Audiocassettes; Personal papers; Oral interpretation of poetry; California (state); Literature; American poetry; American literature; Manuscripts (document genre); Poets; Poetry -- Editing; Novelists; Correspondence; Bolinas (Calif.); Allen, Donald, 1912-2004; Dorn, Edward; Hausman, Gerald; Kherdian, David; Koch, Kenneth, 1925-2002; Ashbery, John, 1927-2017; Malanga, Gerard; Oppenheimer, Joel, 1930-1988; Welch, Lew; Avedon, Richard; Higgins, Dick, 1938-1998; Leary, Timothy, 1920-1996; Whalen, Philip; Waldman, Anne, 1945-; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Matthau, Walter; Matthau, Carol, 1924-2003; Saroyan, William, 1908-1981; McKuen, Rod; Plimpton, George; Plymell, Charles
- Series I: Correspondence, 1974-1977
  - A (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Allen, Donald, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Ashbery, John, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Avedon, Richard, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - B (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Balakian, Nona, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Berkson, Bill, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Bockris, Victor, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Brann, Helen, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Britton, Burt, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Brownstein, Michael, 1975 (Box 1)
  - C (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - D (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Davies, Alan, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Dorn, Ed, 1976 (Box 1)
  - E (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - F (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - G (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - H (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Hausman, Gerald, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Hearst, William, III, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Higgins, Dick, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Hitzig, Karen, 1975 (Box 1)
  - I - J (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - K (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Kherdian, David, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Koch, Kenneth, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Kostelanetz, Richard, 1975 (Box 1)
  - L (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Lapate, Phillip, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Laughlin, James, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Leary, Timothy, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Leonard, John, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Lyons, Sylvia, 1975 (Box 1)
  - M (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Matthau, Carol, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Matthau, Carol and Walter, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Matthau, Carol and Walter, 1977 (Box 1)
  - McClanahan, Grant and Pauli, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - McKuen, Rod, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Moss, Howard, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - N (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Oppenheimer, Joel, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Owen, Maureen, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - P (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Plimpton, George, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Plymell, Charles, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - R (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Raworth, Tom, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - S (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Saroyan, William, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Saroyan Family, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Saroyan Family, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Schjeldahl, Peter, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Sklena, Vincent, and Middleton, F., 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - T (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - V (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - W (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Waldman, Anne, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Wylie, Andrew, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Y (assorted), 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Z (assorted), 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Unknown, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
- Series II: Audio cassettes, 1969-1977
  Access
  Use of audio cassettes requires production of listening copies.
  - Lew Welch interview with David Meltzer, 1969 July 17 (Cassette 1978-0004/AC6)
  - Lew Welch interview, part two, [1969?] (Cassette 1978-0004/AC7)
  - Philip Whalen and Magda Cregg, Side A: September 8, 1976 Side B: November 15, 1976 (Disk 1978-0004_cd1 (rc), Cassette 1978-0004/AC 1)
  - Philip Whalen and Magda Cregg (2nd tape), Side A: September 8, 1976 Side B: November 15, 1976 (Cassette 1978-0004/AC2)
  - Gary Snyder at Jack Hogan's Mill Valley House, 1977 March 1 (Cassette 1978-0004/AC3)
  - Continuation of Talk with Gary Snyder and Jack Hogan in Mill Valley, 1977 March 1 (Cassette 1978-0004/AC4)
  - Interview with Joanne Kyger about Lew Welch, Bolinas, 1977 April 14 (Cassette 1978-0004/AC5)
- Series III: Publications, undated, 1950-1977
  - Photocopy of Saroyan's Personal Bibliography for 1975-1977, circa 1977 (Box 2)
  - Copies of Saroyan's Periodical Print Publications, 1975-1977; (13 items) (Box 2)
  - Copies of Saroyan's Periodical Poetry Publications, 1975-1977; (5 items) (Box 2)
  - Fair Copy/ Typescript of O My Generation and Other Poems, undated (Box 2)
  - Fair Copy Poems: "Poetry Written Down in th Dark," "Timing," "Troubador," "Day," "Poet", undated (Box 2)
  - Fair Copy Poems - Various titles, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "For Armenak Saroyan, My Grandfather", undated (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "The Transparent Man", 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS poem with typescript - "Poem" ("What makes my little son"), 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS poem with typescript - "Spring", 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS poem with typescript - "The House", 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS poem with typescript - "Up in the Loft", 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "For Gailyn", undated (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "The Gift", 1976 (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "When the Heart Melts", 1976 (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "Sonnet" ("I remember the evenings..."), 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "Sonnet" ("I sing the subtle beauty..."), 1976 (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "The Facts", 1976 (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "Domestic Scene", undated (Box 2)
  - MS poem - "Winter Midnight", 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - The Wisdom of the Heart, 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - How to be an American Poet, 1977 (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - Ciciero on Main Street, undated (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - Hello and High, undated (Box 2)
  - MS reviews - Golden Gate and Archetype West, undated (Box 2)
  - MS reviews - Above the Treeline and Death College, undated (Box 2)
  - MS review - Portraits, undated (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of MS - A Letter to My Father and Our Unborn Child, circa1977 (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of MS fair copy -- A Letter to My Father and Our Unborn Child, circa1977 (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - How to Start a Family..., undated (Box 2)
  - MS draft - How to Start a Family and Not Go Permanently Crazy, undated (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - An Interview with Walter Matthau, undated (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - Lew Welch, undated (Box 2)
  - MS typescript - Lew Welch, undated (Box 2)
  - Typed Copy of Lew Welch and the American Heart, with marginal notes by Donald Allen, undated (Box 2)
  - Lew Welc> materials - outline and notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Partial MS and typed drafts of Lew Welch, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes and typed draft of Lew Welch and the American Heart, undated (Box 2)
  - MS typescript -- Lew Welch and the American Heart, undated (Box 2)
  - Handwritten MS for Lew Welch book, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications pertaining to Lew Welch, 1956-1976 (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of The Writing of Gertrude Stein (thesis by Lew Welch), 1950 (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of Poems and Remarks by Lew Welch, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Photocopy of I, Leo, by Lew Welch, undated (Box 2)
  - Copies of Lew Welch's letters (typescript fair copies), 1950-1957 (Box 2)
  - Copies of Lew Welch's letters, vol. II (typescript fair copies), 1958-1961 (Box 2)
  - Copies of Lew Welch's letters, vol. III (typescript fair copies), 1962-1971 (Box 2)
  - Saroyan's contract with the William Morris Agency, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Trinity School (N.Y.) Publications, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Folded posters - "His Holiness Dudjom Rinpoche", undated (Box 2)
  - Flyers for Poetry Readings involving Saroyan, circa 1975-77 (Box 2)
  - Gift from William Anthony - "French Poets" cartoon, undated (Box 2)
  - Various promotional materials, catalogs, circa 1977; (3 items), (Box 2)
  - Posters, undated (Box OS)